Guide to the Ivan Kats Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ivan Kats papers
1948-2006
MS 2048
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.33
(13 boxes)
The Ivan Kats papers are comprised of correspondence, drafts of Obor Foundation publications and translations, Obor Foundation financial information, reports from the Congress for Cultural Freedom, photographs from Kats' travels in Indonesia, and three Indonesian anti-communist posters. Correspondence with journalist, publisher, novelist, and key Obor Foundation contributor Muchtar Lubis, between 1969 and 1983, comprises a large portion of the collection, as does Kats' correspondence with many other Indonesian intellectuals and officials. Of particular interest are the drafts and correspondence related to an unpublished volume, Indonesia 1958-1965: The Cultural Scene which Kats organized between 1966 and 1967. Contributors include Indonesian intellectuals Andre Hardjana, Rosihan Anwar and S. Tasrif, with several drafts in both English and Indonesian.
Kats, Ivan
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in six series: I. Unpublished work, Cultural Scene, 1961-1968. II. The Obor Foundation, 1950-2002. III. The Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1960-1990. IV. 30 September Movement, 1964-1966. V. Personal correspondence and writings, 1948-2006. VI. Photographs and posters, 1965-1966.
Biographical / Historical
Born in the Netherlands, Ivan Kats spent the majority of his adult life in France and the United States, where he worked as a translator, editor, teacher, journalist and publisher. While living in France during the 1960s, Kats worked for the Congress for Cultural Freedom (CCF) – an anti-communist advocacy group founded in Paris – that established magazines, held conferences and art shows, and supported a number of poets, authors, and artists across 35 countries worldwide. Until his departure from the CCF in 1966, Kats was primarily engaged in a program for sending books and other publications to anti-communist, opposition leaders in Indonesia. After the 30 September Movement, and the ouster of the Indonesian President Sukarno in 1967, Kats left France and moved to New Haven, Connecticut, where he became affiliated with the Council on South East Asian Studies at Yale University. Between 1970 and his retirement in 1996, Kats functioned as director of Buku Obor (Yayasan Obor Indonesia), or the Obor Foundation, an organization he founded, dedicated to the publication and dissemination of books to book-poor countries. Initially focused on Indonesia, Obor spread to several other countries including Pakistan and Morocco, where they translated and published books in Urdu and Arabic.
Scope and Contents
The Ivan Kats papers are comprised of correspondence, drafts of Obor Foundation publications and translations, Obor Foundation financial information, reports from the Congress for Cultural Freedom, photographs from Kats' travels in Indonesia, and three Indonesian anti-communist posters. Correspondence with journalist, publisher, novelist, and key Obor Foundation contributor Muchtar Lubis, between 1969 and 1983, comprises a large portion of the collection, as does Kats' correspondence with many other Indonesian intellectuals and officials. Of particular interest are the drafts and correspondence related to an unpublished volume, Indonesia 1958-1965: The Cultural Scene which Kats organized between 1966 and 1967. Contributors include Indonesian intellectuals Andre Hardjana, Rosihan Anwar and S. Tasrif, with several drafts in both English and Indonesian.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nicolas Kats, 2008. Transferred from the Southeast Asia Collection Curator, 2016.
Indonesia; Indonesia -- History -- Coup d'etat, 1965; Anti-communist movements; Kats, Ivan; Obor Foundation; Congress for Cultural Freedom
- Cultural Scene, 1961-1968; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes drafts, outlines of articles, and related correspondence for the unpublished essay collection Cultural Scene. Cultural Scene was proposed to discuss academic and cultural life in Indonesia in the seven years preceding the 30 September movement. Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Article drafts
    - "Cultural Situation in Indonesia 1958-1965," description and outline, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Prologue. by Anak Agung Gde Agung, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Indonesia 1958-1965: The Intellectual Opposition to Guided Democracy," by Ivan Kats, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Indonesian Elite Cadre in Europe 1958-1965," by E.J. Sutarte Hardjosusono, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Godless that Failed: How Indonesian Communists Manipulated News," by J.O. Soendoro, 1967 August (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Fragments from a 'Djakarta Diary,'" by Rosihan Anwar, part I, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Fragments from a 'Djakarta Diary,'" by Rosihan Anwar, part II, 1962–1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Fragments from a 'Djakarta Diary,'" by Rosihan Anwar, part III, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Fragments from a 'Djakarta Diary,'" by Rosihan Anwar, part IV concluded, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Fragments from a 'Djakarta Diary,'" by Rosihan Anwar, final edited version, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "'Basis' in the Middle of the Cultural Struggle in Indonesia," by Ahar/Andre Hardjana, 1967 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "The Struggle for Intellectual Freedom in Indonesia, 1957-1965," by Wiratmo Soekino, 1966 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Notes on the Disturbed Conditions…" by Slamet Rahardjo, 1967 March (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "A Testimonial Story of an Indonesian Student," by Ahar/ Andre Hardjana, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "The Toils of the Indonesian Press: A Personal Remembrance," by S. Tasrif, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Academic Freedom: A Case Study," by Haryati Soebadio, 1967 January (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Portrait of a Young Poet as Malin Kundang," by Goenavan Mohamad, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "The Struggle of a Little Magazine," by Dick Geldrop, 1967 October (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Political Forces in Modern Indonesian Literature," by Arief Budiman, 1970 July (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "The Battle at the Campus…" by Mochtar Buchori, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "Notes of a Book-seller," by Mr. Hazil (Tanzil), 1967 March (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Student Politics in Indonesia," by Soe Hok-Gie, 1969 August (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "National Personality: The Cultural Challenge," by Trisno Sumardjo, 1967 April (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "Herinneringen aan Sjahir," by Sjahrir, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Appendix I: "Three Discussions on Freedom," by Rosihan Anway/Mochtar Lubis/S. Tasrif, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Appendix II: "Indonesian Press Rides New Waves," by S. Tasrif, Circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Appendix III: "Indonesia's Basic Press Law of 1966," by S. Tasrif, Circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence with contributors
    - Agung, Anak Agung Gde, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Anwar, Rosihan, 1965–1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Arbi, Sutan Zanti, 1967 February 7 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Assegaff, D.H., 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Auwjong, P.K., 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Diponegoro, Mohammad, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Djajadiningrat, S., 1967 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Djohan, Bahder, 1967 March 13 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Geldorp, Dick, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Gunawan, Muhammad, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Hardjana, Andre, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Hardjosusono, E.J. Sutarte, 1967 June–1967 August (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Hartowardojo, S. Harijadi, 1966 July–1966 September (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Hatta, Mohammad, 1967 March–1967 June (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Hazil, (Tanzil), 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Holt, Claire, 1967 September 26 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ismael, Twefiq, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Jassin, H.B., 1966 June–1966 September (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Johns, Professor, 1967 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Koesno, Mohammad, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Lombogia, W.A.G., 1966 August–1966 December (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lubis, Mochtar, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Moedigdo, Paul, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Notohamidjojo, O., 1967 June (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Rahardjo, Slamet, 1967 November (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Rendra, W.S., 1967 June (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Rosjadi, Imron, 1967 June (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Rozy, Mohammad Fachrur, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Simatupang, Gen. T.B., 1967 March–1967 September (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Soe, Hok Djin, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Soe, Hok Gie, 1966 April–1966 October (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Soebadio, Haryati, 1968 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Soekito, Wiratmo, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Sumardjo, Trisno, 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Sumitro, Djoko, 1967 February (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Tasrif, S., 1968 September–1968 October (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Zen, M.T., 1966–1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- The Obor Foundation, 1950-2002; Series II
  The series includes correspondence, publications, financial documents, and other official documents pertaining to the Obor Foundation, the nonprofit organization that Kats founded and directed. Arranged by document type.
  - Correspondence from Mochtar Lubis, 1969-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
  - General correspondence
    - al Mujahid, Sharif, 2002 January 23 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Anderton, Donna, 1977–1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Auwjong, P.K., 1966 October 13–1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Boen, Kiok Lie, 1966 September 1–1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Buchori, Mochtar, 1966–1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Buddiman, Arief, 1967 September 20 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Dagg, Chris, 1967 May 22 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Drift, S.J. (L.v.d.), 1967 February (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Driss, 1997 May 23 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Erhardy, 1997 May 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Gonzalez-Quijano, Yves, 1997 May 9 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Ma'ruf, Anas, 1966 July–1966 September (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - McNeeley, Dr. Jeffery A., 1983 April 12 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Mochtar, Kustinyati, 1975 February 12 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Morgan, Kenneth, 1973 November 8 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Riekerk, G.H.M., 1966 March–1966 December (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Said, Mohamad, 1967 June (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Slamet, Boen Oemarjati, 1967 April–1967 June (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Soedjatmoko, S., 1965–1967 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Soendoro, 1966–1967 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Steinberg, David I., 1966 October 1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Tjiahengan, Roy, 1966 October (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - W. Heffer Sons Ltd., 1973 June 19 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Yth, Kepada, 1983 June 1 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Finances
    - Rockefeller Brothers Fund Agreement, 1985 April 9 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Obor Budget Reports, 1997–1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - United States Agency for International Development financial reports
      - First quarter, 1979 August–1979 November (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Second quarter, 1979 November–1980 February (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Third quarter, 1980 February–1980 May (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Fourth quarter, 1980 May–1980 August (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Fifth quarter, 1980 August–1980 November (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Sixth quarter, 1980 November–1981 February (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Seventh quarter, 1981 February–1981 May (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Eighth quarter, 1981 May–1981 August (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Ninth quarter, 1981 August–1981 November (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Tenth quarter, 1981 November–1982 February (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Eleventh quarter, 1982 February–1982 May (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Twelfth quarter, 1982 May–1982 August (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Thirteenth quarter, 1982 August–1982 November (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Fourteenth quarter, 1982 November–1983 February (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Fifteenth quarter, 1983 February–1983 May (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Obor Foundation publications
    - Mochtar Buchori curriculum vitae and writing, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Economic Development as a Cultural Problem by Soedjatmoko, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - An Approach to Indonesian History Towards an Open Future by Soedjatmoko, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - The "Cultural Manifesto" Affair... by Goenawan Mohamad, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - From Mochtar Lubis' Tjatatan Dalam Tahanan (notes from the detention barraks) by P.K. Auwjong, Circa 1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - "Djuga Engkaw Brutus…" by M.T. Zen, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Lampiran by H.H.M. Riekert, Circa 1957-circa 1959 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Introduction to untitled work by Professor Johns, Circa 1967 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Introduction to untitled work by Pierre Crapon de Caprona, 1978–1981 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Obor Foundation related documents
    - Obor Board of Trustees documentation, 1997 May 31 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Obor, purpose, 1988 July (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Obor publication list, 1973–1994 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Obor pamphlets, Circa 1996 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Ivan Kats retirement memories and tributes, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Intermediate Technology Bookshop publication list, 1981–1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Bellagio Publishing Network Newsletter, 1992 January–1997 March (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Bellagio Publishing Network Newsletter, 1996 July–2002 November (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Studies on Books and Reading No. 4 and No. 5, 1981–1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Asian/Pacific Book Development Quarterly 1995 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - CEU Press Translation Project List, Circa 1996 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Obor Foundation activities in Morocco and Vietnam
    - Documentation on Obor Publishing in Morocco, 1984–1995 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Summary of publishing in North Africa, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Ivan Kats notebooks from Rockefeller sponsored conferences, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence on Obor Arab Project, 1995–1997 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Obor work in Vietnam, 1995 October (Box 8, Folder 5)
- The Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1960-1990; Series III
  This series consists of reports and articles written by and on the Congress for Cultural Freedom (CCF), an anti-Communist organization. The documents focus on general work by the CCF, including work done in Asia, but do not focus on Kats's specific projects.
  - "A Report on 10 Years of Activity", 1960 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Congress Informations Pour la Liberté de la Culture: April-May 1960/March-May 1964", 1960–1964 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Towards the Open Community: Human Ideals and Social Difficulties", 1963 December (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Student Organization Resolutions by Djoesma Said", 1965 May 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Report to the Ford Foundation on Western European Studies and Opinion on East Asia: October 12, 1965", 1965 October 12 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "The Asian Institute of International Relations: A Proposal", Circa 1966 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "What was the Congress for Cultural Freedom? By Hilton Kramer", 1990 October (Box 9, Folder 7)
- 30 September Movement, 1964-1966; Series IV
  This series contains handwritten and typed reports on the 30 September Movement, information on the members of the movement, and a newspaper article. Some of the material appears to be written by Kats.
  - Reports on the 30 September Movement, 1964–1966 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - List of Indonesian intellectuals and press with notes, 1965–1966 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Graveside Eulogy Rallies a Nation," clipping from The Australian, 1966 April 28 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Personal correspondence and writings, 1948-2006; Series V
  This series includes correspondence with individuals and a small amount of writing, mainly related to the Obor Foundation. None of the correspondence is exhaustive; there are one or two letters or packets per correspondent.
  - Correspondence with individuals
    - General, 1979–1983 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Clifford, 1956–1964 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Dharampal, Shri, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Jose, Frankie, 2006 January 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Roberts, Burgert, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Writings
    - Doctoral dissertation fragment: December 24, 1948, 1948 December 24 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - How to Develop a Publishing Industry in a Book-Poor Country, Circa 1968 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - The Story of the Obor Foundation: An Indonesian Experience for Replication?, 1992 July (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Photographs and posters, 1965-1996; Series VI
  This series contains photographs of Kats and colleagues as well as three anti-Communist posters.
  - Photographs of Ivan Kats and associates during work with Obor Foundation, Circa 1966-1996 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "Su Bandrio Andjing (Anjing) Peking", Circa 1965 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Two folded hand painted posters.
  - "Su Bandrio Andjing (Anjing) Peking", Circa 1965 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    One hand painted poster.